Who was my mother?
Aloy, I've told you before, that's not for us to know.
You were just a newborn when
the Matriarchs brought you to me.
So the Matriarchs, they know?
It's not so simple.
But they know?
Aloy, we are outcasts.
So how do I make them tell me?
The Matriarchs? There is a way, perhaps…
So tell me.
It would be dangerous.
How?
It would take years of training.
I don't care.
How do I do it?
Tell me!
The Proving!
The tribe's rite of passage held every year.
Those who pass become Braves.
But to the one who wins,
the Matriarchs grant a boon.
A boon?
Yes, whatever the winner wants.
Aloy, we must speak.
So, it's time.
Are you ready?
Yes. I guess.
It's louder than I expected.
You've never been so close before.
I guess everything's bigger up close.
Soon it'll all seem familiar.
Like home.
I don't know about that.
Look for High Matriarch Teersa.
She'll help you.
Any other concerns?
Any final lessons before I head in?
No. You've learned every lesson the wilds had to teach.
It was you who taught me, not the wilds.
Not sure my bow and spear
will be much help in there though.
It is with bow and spear that you'll win
what you've wanted all these years, Aloy.
Answers.
What should I expect once I'm inside?
There will be people celebrating and feasting.
More than you've ever seen in one place.
No other village compares to Mother's Heart.
It is the seat of the High Matriarchs.
A centre of Nora life.
A jewel of the sacred land.
Give it time.
And you will grow fond of it, as I was.
Back when I was of the tribe.
Are you sure they're gonna let me in?
I've told you, Aloy.
By law any child outcast can run in the Proving.
And any who pass are made Braves
and are outcast no more.
I know that.
But not everyone follows the law like you do, Rost.
Have faith Aloy. The tribe will honour your right.
I'm ready to do this.
See you back home in a few days?
You will not find me there Aloy.
Here.
Take this to…
…remember.
Why are you talking like we'll never see each other again?
No.
No!
You should be with the tribe.
And I will always be an outcast.
But I told you I have that figured out.
I'll come to you in secret.
I'll be the one breaking the law, not you.
You don't even have to talk to me.
This…
…attachment to me will only hold you back.
It's my wish that you embrace the tribe.
You've lived in isolation long enough.
Not until now I didn't.
For your sake I must go where you will never find me.
This…
…this is goodbye.
No! It's not!
You taught me how to track.
Wherever you go I can follow.
Not this time.
I see.
I'm glad to have this then.
It will remind me of you.
Of everything you did.
And how you helped prepare me for this day.
Thank you.
Heavier than it looks.
But the cord is strong.
May All-Mother bless you, Aloy.
And you.
How could he do this?
Today of all days.
I have to let him go.
For now.
First the Proving, after that I'll see where his trail leads.
You will turn back Outcast.
Or bleed.
Your choice.
[in distance]
Make way!
Make way! Make way!
Braves stand aside! She is welcome here.
Mother's Heart is open to you child.
Come!
I assure you most Nora aren't so rude as those idiots.
You're Teersa?
[laughs] Who else would I be?
Come on now!
I've been waiting for this day a long time.
You have?
Oh yes.
But for the moment I must leave you.
I have other outsiders to keep safe tonight.
You … what?
Envoys from another tribe, the Carja.
Come to observe the Proving.
And oh, how the Nora hate the Carja.
"Carja."
But that's my problem.
We will talk later.
In the meantime enjoy the festival.
Oh, down the path to the right you'll find
an old friend who can't wait to see you.
But I don't know anyone here.
[laughs] Try telling him that.
We will talk later. May the Goddess protect!
What is going on?
[constant drumming]
[crowd member] The festival before
my sister's proving had much better music.
[in the distance]
Aloy! It's you isn't it?
Over here!
It is Aloy isn't it?I'm remembering your name correctly?
Are you the old friend Teersa told me about?
I don't know you.
I see you don't recognise me.
Well it was a long time ago.
Teb is my name.
You were half my size when you saved me from a herd of machines.
I remember.
You tried to thank me.
I never forgot that day
All these years I hoped to see you again,
if you came to run in the Proving.
As you can see, I didn't turn out to be much of a Hunter.
I serve the tribe as a Stitcher instead.
A maker of garments and armour.
In preparation for this day I've made an outfit for you.
I hope you like it.
What's it going to cost?
Cost? Nothing.
Consider it the thanks I tried to give years ago.
Long overdue.
There.
Seems to fit you perfectly.
Uh, thank you Teb.
I've never had anything like this before.
Well it's yours.
I think you'll find it affords more protection
than what you were wearing.
Anyway.
I hsouldn't keep you any longer.
Head for the Matriarch's Lodge
if you want to find Teersa.
You'll know it when you see it.
A large wooden building
with an angry mob waiting outside.
Teersa said something about
envoys from another tribe?
Yes. That's what the mob is angry about.
Carja visiting our Sacred Land for the first time in years.
I'd expect to see some tomatoes flying.
Maybe rocks.
Hopefully not spears.
In any case be ready to duck.
🎼
[singing in another language]
Jarg! Get down from there!
Bad enough you're drunk,
why do you have to go climbing houses?
Oh not supposed to go
climbing on other people's roofs huh?
Get down from there, now!
That's just what you want isn't it?
For me to fall on my head.
What I want is for you to climb down!
What you want is for me to have no fun at all.
Fine! Stay up on the roof all night if you want!
Yeah I will!
What an idiot he is.
Every year this happens. Every year.
At least he's not trying to run a Brave Trail.
She can't tell me what to do.
I'll climb so far up she can't see me.
Wasn't drunk when I ran the Proving!
Might've won.
[in the distance]
Listen carefully now…
…for you'll have to tell this when I'm gone.
[in the distance]
In the beginning all life came from All-Mother.
People, machines, and beasts.
All were Her children.
They lived alongside each other in
the comfort of Her wild embrace.
But some grew restless.
Though they took of Her bounty, they wanted more.
These were the Faithless.
The machines had whispered to them.
Promised to serve them.
To make them a new world,
better than the one All-Mother provided.
A world of metal.
They told the Faithless they would do all the work for them.
Feed them, shelter them, give them a life of ease.
Of plenty.
And so the Faithless left with the machines.
Only the true children,
the mothers and fathers of the Nora,
stayed with All-Mother.
At first, the machines did as they had promised.
They built cities, great and terrible.
Monuments to their sins.
But they would not serve the Faithless for long.
A king rose up among the machines.
A machine more powerful than any other.
The Metal Devil.
And then the Faithless served him.
Served the machines.
That was not enough for the Metal Devil.
He wanted all to serve him.
And tried to tempt the true children away from All-Mother.
They would not go.
They gathered on the mountainside to cling to Her,
and prayed more devoted than ever.
The Metal Devil raged louder than thunder.
In his fury, he came to confront All-Mother.
Intending to kill Her.
She struck him down.
Forever.
As you know, for his lifeless body is up there still.
Frozen in shame and defeat.
The machines were driven mad by the death of their king.
And their minds became as wild as beasts.
The Faithless abandoned their cities.
Forced to wander the world without the care of the machines.
Only we remain the true children of All-Mother.
We built all this with the hands that She gave us.
Machines are to be hunted.
Metal to be used for scrap, for craft.
But never to be adored.
And we stay true to H er laws,
resolute in our prayers, don't we?
For the dangers are never over.
Still the Faithless envy our Sacred Land and covet it.
And year upon year the machines anger grows.
Searching for little Nora boys and girls who have not behaved.
[gasp] What? Is that a machine among us now?
No, no. These old eyes are mistaken.
[crowd member]
Bast's a bully. He won't last a minute against Vala.
Not in a real fight.
[in the distance]
Aloy! Over here!
Karst?
What are you doing here?
Careful. Pretend like we've never met.
I wasn't supposed to trade with outcasts
in the wilds, remember?
How could I forget?
And how generous of you to talk to me now.
Don't be like that.
You know I'll be rooting for you in the Proving tomorrow.
Can't wait to see the looks
on some of these faces when you win.
And if you need any last minute supplies I'm your man.
So, Mother's Heart.
I thought you preferred the wilds.
Well, a man can't drink alone all the time can he?
Truth is I get lonely once in a while.
There. I admitted it.
Don't think less of me.
I won't hold it against you if you give me a discount.
You can't be…
I'm joking Karst.
It's good to see you.
Don't go soft on me.
Alright, let's do this.
Until next time.
Next time you'll be a Brave.
[gong rings]
In a moment, we shall bless the Proving.
But first…
…we have guests to welcome.
For two years we have been at peace with the Carja.
It is time to restore our bonds of trade with Meridian.
These envoys come to us under a banner of peace.
An annunciation of gratitude written…
[crowd]
Killers and slavers!
Yeah! Killers and slavers!
Hey! Hey! Hold your fruit!
Nora … Nora faithful, hold your fruit.
Now I'm Oseram, not Carja.
So I'll put it to you straight.
The thirtheenth Sun King
was a murderous bum.
He was!
He was a tyrant and a monster…
Raided my tribe for blood sacrifice just like yours.
My own sister was taken.
I hated the Carja.
But the thirteenth King is dead.
Two years now.
And who killed him? The fourteenth.
Not because he lusted for power.
But because someone had to put an end
to his father's atrocities.
Yeah!
The message that this poor priest
means to read is an apology.
Straight from the lips of the fourteenth King.
So please…
…can't you lend him your ears?
Thank you.
An annunciation of gratitude written
by the hand of Sun-King Avad.
Fourteenth Luminance of the Radiant Line.
Looks like it's on that bald man.
One of the visitors.
"Unknown device detected"?
What does that mean?
He's wearing a Focus. Just like mine.
You're the only other person I've ever seen
wearing a Focus.
Where did you get yours?
What? A Nora wearing one of these?
That's impossible.
Your tribe fears the old places, forbids them!
Who says I'm like other Nora?
Why yeah, I guess you're not if you've gone
delving in the ruins of the Metal World.
Olin!
You making friends with the locals are we?
Aah!
What's wrong?
Apologies. Uhh … a malfunction. I'll come back.
Wait!
No, we'll talk later. Have to go.
Whoa. I guess he's more hungover than I thought.
Hey.
You've got the same trinket that Olin has on his head.
Since when did those become fashionable?
His name is Olin?
Who is he?
And where did he get one of these?
He's just a scrounger with friends in high places.
He spends half his time digging for artifacts,
the other half drinking or dicing.
As for the trinket, I guess he dug it up somewhere.
Just a weird old jewel he sticks on his face.
No offence.
It looks great on you.
What else do you know about Olin?
Is he really that interesting?
I'm starting to get jealous.
Well he scours the wilds for ruins.
Digs up stuff and sells it to nobles.
When he's not scrounging, he's scouting.
Exactly the skills you want the man
guarding your expedition to have.
I've known him for a few years.
He's a loyal companion, cares for his family,
and holds his drink well enough.
I like him, but besides that not much to tell.
I've never seen armour like yours before.
You've never seen Vanguard steel?
Let me introduce you.
Ring-locked, impact protected,
sturdy enough to choke a Sawtooth.
It has to be.
The Vanguard are the Sun-King's best.
Life takers and machine breakers to a one.
Might even give a Nora Warmaid like you
more trouble than she can handle.
[laugh] With all that metal to slow you down?
I doubt it.
Yeah, hard to say.
From where I'm standing looks like a pretty even match.
I thought your friend was gonna
go down in a hail of fruit…
…but you really calmed the crowd.
Thanks. I wasn't sure I could do it.
The Nora are still pissed with the Carja about the Red Raids.
And who can blame them?
I never heard anything about Red Raids growing up.
What were those?
Your tribe was at war and you didn't even know?
Were you kept hidden away?
Did you have over-protective parents or something?
I grew up as an Outcast.
Shunned by the tribe.
Oh. I've heard the Nora do that.
Seems cruel if you ask me.
But even an Outcast knows about
the Derangement of the Machines right?
How they get deadlier every year?
First I've heard of it.
Oh. Sorry I just assumed everyone knew.
The way I hear it fifteen, twenty, years ago
the machines weren't always pissed off
like they are now.
When a Hunter came at them they'd spook and run.
So it was hard to take them down
but not dangerous.
So long as you were smart enough
to jump out of the way.
But then the Derangement starts up
and everything changes.
Now when a Hunter fires a shot
the machines snarl and charge right at him.
Few more years pass,
and they start attacking people on sight.
Going anywhere becomes a major risk.
If that wasn't bad enough,
entirely new kinds of machines start showing up.
Bigger, meaner, and heavily armed.
Like the Sawtooth?
Yeah, ten years ago that one.
But every couple of years or so
something worse comes along.
Belive me.
So what's making it happen?
No-one knows.
The Mad Sun-King figured if he spilled enough blood
to the Sun-God it would calm the machines.
Didn't work.
But for years he raided the tribes
and took captives for sacrifice.
My sister among them.
Your sister was taken captive and sacrificed?
That's terrible.
Ha! Captive, yes. Sacrificed? No.
It takes more than a few Carja to finish Ersa.
She got away and now she's my captain.
Captain of the entire Vanguard.
Favoured by the Sun-King himself.
How did she survive?
Well that's a story alright.
But it takes a while to tell.
Maybe another time over a drink or three?
Or just come to Meridian and meet her yourself.
I think you'd like each other,
you're both rather … ah … direct.
So what happened? How did it all end?
The Mad King's own son united
Carja rebels with Oseram Freebooters.
Together we did the impossible.
Took back Meridian and killed the crazy old king.
Who are the Oseram?
That's my tribe.
Far to the North-West.
We're good at three things.
Arguing, working steel, and brewing.
And "Freebooters"? What are those?
I guess you could say we were mercenaries.
You know, warriors for pay.
Except a lot more loyal than that makes us sound.
Avad couldn't have taken down his father
without our metal and muscle.
And now some of us serve proudly
as his personal Vanguard.
If the Carja have such a cruel history
how did you end up serving them?
The last king and his men were butchers.
But the new king wants peace.
There's nothing cruel about that.
Under Avad there's no more sacrifices,
no more slavery.
Besides, the Carja don't just fight, they build.
Take Meridian.
Next to it, everything else
is just a bunch of sticks and stones.
What's it like?
Where do I even start?
My tribesmen are masters of the forge.
The best tinkers in the world.
But when it comes to building,
the Carja have us beat.
The city soars over a canyon with more bridges than the Nora have roads and buildings tall as mountains.
And across the valley stands the Spire.
Like a blade thrust into the sky,
reflecting the sun.
You really owe it to yourself to see it.
So consider that a challenge.
Or an invitation.
I should make my way to the Blessing.
Yeah. Look, maybe I shouldn't say this, but…
…it's obvious that you don't belong in this backwater.
I mean, you're smart, you're obviously capable and…
Well, I mean, look at you.
Err, what are you talking about?
You know what!
Alright, if you ever visit Meridian look me up.
I'll show you around, make introductions.
It'd be a whole new life. If you want it.
Anyway, I have to go to that Blessing thing too.
See you around? Maybe?
[in the distance]
We'll start the Blessing when all aspirants are in place.
Oh!
Expecting more tomatoes?
In truth I thought they were throwing stones.
Stones hit a lot harder,
you'd know the difference.
If you wish to speak,
we should do so after the ceremony.
I'd rather not hold things up.
Or do anything else that angers these people.
Let's talk after the Blessing.
I don't want to piss off the Matriarchs.
Those are some tough looking grandmothers.
Aloy, take your place right there.
The prayer lantern is yours.
I made it for you.
Blaspemy.
Sisters.
Aspirants! Before each of you sits a prayer lantern
crafted by your mother.
In her honour, light its flame.
In honour of Rost.
And all he did to help me get here.
[Matriarchs together]
All-Mother! Hear our prayer!
What is the child but a mother's hope that takes flight?
[Matriarchs together]
A glowing flame that climbs the air.
Set free to the wind, sailing the sky.
[Matriarchs together]
Until it fades and falls.
So from one to another, passes the chain of love.
There's Olin. I have some questions for him.
Aloy.
Now that the Blessing has been made,
you and I finally have a moment to speak.
I hope the ceremony wasn't
too unpleasant for you.
Given your circumstances.
I can't say it was comfortable,
but I could see the beauty
of the ritual even so.
It takes a generous heart, Aloy,
to commend a ritual that venerates
all that you were denied.
All I'm saying is that it didn't bother me.
I have bigger things to worry about
than hearing the Nora mumble about their mothers.
I see.
Rost told me that Matriarchs don't just lead the tribe.
What else do you do?
We teach. Offer counsel.
Give blessings.
When necessary, we judge.
Our only concern is the welfare of the tribe.
Among our number this year
we count three High Matriarchs,
and some thirty lesser Matriarchs.
What's the difference?
Matriarchs are grandmothers,
with two generations of living progeny.
But a High Matriarch is a great-grandmother.
With three or more generations to her name.
Thus do we speak for generations,
lending our opinions weight.
The High Matriarchs most of all.
So the more children you have
the more authority you get?
I guess that's one way to decide who leads a tribe.
Why would there be any other?
Just so you know, Teersa,
the reason I'm here is to get answers.
Real ones.
And when I win the Proving Iwill demand them.
I know, Aloy. I would expect nothing less.
Why was I made an Outcast at birth, Teersa?
What crime could I have committed even before I was born?
Aloy! This is not a question I can answer.
Why not? It's simple enough.
And what about my mother?
Is she here tonight watching me?
Or is she dead?
I am sure your mother is here with us.
If only in spirit.
That's not really an answer, is it?
What about Rost?
Why was he made an Outcast?
So he never told you?
He said he swore an oath never to speak of it.
Yes. As did I.
And the other Matriarchs.
I'm sorry, Aloy. But Rost's past
is another secret I must keep from you.
It's surprises me the tribe lets outcasts run in the Proving.
It's not like the Nora to be so hospitable.
It has alwys been law that any child outcast has this right.
As a means to rejoin the tribe.
So far as I know, however,
you are the first ever to exercise this right.
I'm not surprised.
I doubt many outcast children survive
long enough in the wilds to come of age.
I think rather it is because child outcasts are so rare.
In all my years I've only known
of one other child who was cast out.
A boy of thirteen.
Who killed his mother.
But at the Proving five years later,
he did not appear.
No.
I'd be surprised if he survived very long on his own.
But at least he had a chance.
Other tribes would've simply executed him.
It may be hard for you to accept, Aloy.
But the practice of shunning is,
relatively speaking, humane.
Oh is it?
Try it out for eighteen years Teersa,
and then let me know what you think.
You're not the only one
who's waited years for this day.
I will be praying for your success.
That blessing wasn't so bad.
Nice and short anyway.
But I know a half-dozen Oseram tinkers
who could put on a better fireworks show.
Oops
I hope I'm not throwing a wet blanket
on your sacred ritual.
It was nice.
Really.
Good luck in that Proving thing.
Maybe I'll see you in Meridian some day,
who knows?
You have already been blessed, but…
May the dawn find you,
the day warm you,
and the dusk have light to guide your path.
Who are you Sun Priest?
I am the Reverend Irid.
The glory of the Carja is the Sun's glory reflected.
We Sun Priests are but glimmers of its great light.
You just said a lot,
but you didn't tell me anything.
My apologies.
My duty is to carry out the will of the Sun,
by serving its emissary among us the Sun-King.
I comfort those who walk by the light of day.
And I travel to those in far reaches
whom the light barely touches, bearing warmth.
But here among you I see
a beauty that shines true.
Perhaps Namman is right after all.
That the Sun's light brightens
all lands, and all peoples.
Who's Namman?
One of my bretheren.
Who believes that the sky is wide enough
for the faiths of all tribes.
But you don't believe in All-Mother do you?
Usually the distance between our tribes shrouds Nora ways from Carja eyes.
So you live in Meridian?
I do. Where better to mark the Sun's divine passage
than where the sandstone glows
in the light of its passing?
I was raised in the mesa's great shade.
Its wild bird markets and metal sellers,
spices, and coloured silks!
Sounds impressive.
Oh you should behold it.
And you can if you make the journey.
At His Luminance's order we have
flung its gates open to all!
Did you come all this way just to deliver your Sun-King's speech?
It is my duty. And also my honour.
To carry the light of atonement to those
we overshadowed and wronged.
Under the thirteenth Sun-King
the Carja had no peace with any tribe.
His Luminance has sent those days to dusk.
We must renew the light that binds us.
Though few volunteered to come here.
The Nora scare you?
They're good at making people feel unwelcome.
It's said one soldier died for every Nora taken alive.
Who is the Sun-King you speak for?
His Luminance Avad is the
fourteenth king of the Radiant Line.
His light envelops the sky and everything beneath it.
He is the chosen of the Sun.
By his divine rule we are given sight and purpose.
You speak highly of him.
Do you know him well?
By his nature he is unknowable and infallible.
He's the Sun, he has total power, and no friends.
That couldn't go wrong.
We are his instruments, not his companions.
I have been in his presence,
but we draw down our hoods
so as not to behold his light directly.
If your Sun-Kings are so infallible
how do you explain the crimes of the last king?
Uh, well, the Sun's glory is a great and brazen crown
for a vessel as small as a man.
If the vessel is flawed…
Indeed in the burial caves one can see
the skulls of the past kings are cracked.
Trialled and fired in the Sun's kiln.
That can be too much for any man to bear.
Even a ruler of men.
So the Sun can make bad choices like anyone else?
Oh! No, no, no.
Has there ever been a Sun-Queen?
Err, many wives and consorts of course.
Or … oh! You mean for the Sun to choose a queen.
Ah ho ho, this has not happened.
I don't know if you've noticed
but women run things around here.
Well…
Avad took a woman as captain of his Vanguard.
The first to hold such an honour.
You mean Erend's sister, Ersa?
From what he told me she sounds formidable.
Oh! Formidable indeed!
A woman and an outsider as well.
She might make a fine Sun-Queen?
Given a chance?
A Sun-Qu– ho ho ho, oh no no no.
No.
Why not?
Er, the Sun is masculine of course.
And so would choose its heirs thus.
Um.It's a light in the sky.
I've never seen anything dangling from it.
This has been … illuminating?
But I should get going.
Hello Olin.
You know my name?
Ah. Guess Erend told you.
Why did you act so strange when we spoke earlier?
Must be this festival.
I'm really not one for crowds.
Maybe I should just turn in.
Stop dodging my questions.
Alright. Cool your fire.
I got nothing to hide.
What are you doing here, Olin?
Why come to Nora land?
Erend needed a scout for his expedition.
And a second for his drinking.
That's all.
Someone to stop the Sun Priest getting lost.
When all this is over, I'm back to delving ruins.
Rummaging for scrap.
Scrounging up trinkets to sell.
So you're an explorer?
Just another outlander, girl.
A man's got to make his shards.
I just make mine in service to the king's court.
That's all.
I've never seen anyone else with a Focus.
Where exactly did you find it?
In a ruin, north of the Claim.
That's our name for the Oseram homeland.
Up there the metal seams run deep.
Steel giants half buried in loose soil.
Forgotten caves that the Old Ones
bored into mountain rock.
Your face just lit up?
I found my Focus in a cave
just like you're describing.
A ruin of the Old Ones.
If you've delved yourself, you know as much as I do.
Go to those places for answers, not me.
When we spoke earlier, you winced,
then looked like you were in pain.
Or frightened.
Did your Focus show you something?
It didn't show me anything.
I told you, it malfunctioned.
Happens all the time.
You're not a very convincing liar.
Do you always accuse people you've just met of lying?
Only the ones who aren't telling the truth.
Fire and spit, girl!
I'm a plain hammered man with nothing to hide.
You don't believe me, that's your trouble not mine.
I don't understand.
We have this device in common,
but you can't wait to stop talking to me.
[sighs]
I already have all the friends I need, girl.
I don't need the bother.
I'm used to being shunned by the tribe.
I thought you'd be different.
It's nothing personal.
It really isn't.
You should…
…try to enjoy yourself tonight.
Big day tomorrow.
Always best to make every day count.
[constant drumming]
Motherless chuff.
What did you say?
Find your bed, outcast,
and dream of winning the Proving.
That's the closest you're gonna get.
Oh. Is this the bedhouse?
With you standing guard,
I figured it was the latrine.
Your very presence here… uh.
Well, well. Look who's come in from the wild.
The motherless outcast.
You can be a real lard sometimes Bast.
Cut it out.
You didn't know the words to the Blessing did you?
But no-one heards your prayers anyway.
Aww, you even try to dress like a real Nora.
Not that it fools anyone.
So this is how it's gonna be with you is it?
This is how it's gonna be with everyone, outcast.
You belong in the wilds, not in Mother's Heart.
And you definitely don't belong in the Proving.
You can sense it.
You already know you're going to lose.
Hah! I've trained all my life for the Proving.
I'm not afraid of you, I'm not afraid of anything!
Really?
Confidence is quiet, you're not.
You know I often think of the day I gave you that scar.
It's a cherished memory.
Yeah.
The look on your face
when I knocked that stone out of your hand
was pretty entertaining.
But I suppose you leave
that part of the story out when you tell it,
don't you?
I branded you that day to mark your shame.
All you did that day was make me stronger.
Just wait.
I'll show you tomorrow.
Hah! Yeah, right.
This is boring.
Time for Bast to get some sleep.
You'll be the one surprised tomorrow, outcast, not me.
Oh are you going to shut your mouth?
Because that would be a surprise!
Nice job handling Bast.
That should keep him quiet…
'til morning anyway.
I don't believe we've met. I'm Aloy.
Oh I know who you are.
The competition.
The others they'll finish the Proving.
Most of them.
But win it?
That's down to Bast, you, or me.
Vala.
Nice to meet you, Vala.
You're right. I am going to win tomorrow.
Never celebrate a victory before it's earned, girl.
My mother taught me that.
Now, if you'll excuse me,
I'm going to get some sleep.
I plan to be well rested
when I run you into the ground tomorrow.
[laughs]
Your bunk's right there, when you want it.
Okay. Thanks.
So, your first day in Mother's Heart.
What do you think?
You've never slept in a Nora lodge before.
Not very private.
Comforts and distractions, that's what I think.
Not all comforts are bad.
Comforts are weakness.
You sound just like my mother.
It has … certain charms.
Homey enough once you're accepted.
That's the problem.
I think you'll find a place here.
I do. Get some rest.
Braves! Ready yourselves!
What will it take to get you out of here?
Grazers!
Your trophy is shattered, outcast!
Looks like you'll need another.
Faster, come on!
I've gotta catch up!
[in the distance]
Slow and steady now!
All you need is to finish.
[in the distance]
That makes all but one.
Is the outcast coming?
[in the distance]
She was behind me!
Dead last, girl.
Might as well walk from here.
Bast will win, or Vala.
But you'll be made a Brave so long as you finish.
Ooh now, that's an old trail.
Two died on it last year.
It's falling apart.
Better dead last than dead altogether.
Whoa, whoa, whoa, whoa!
By All-Mother, are you crazy?
You're gonna kill yourself!
It doesn't get any easier!
You're insane to go that way!
No way but forward now.
[in the distance]
Who's in the lead?
I can't see.
[in the distance]
Bast. Or Vala.
Come on now!
Faster! Stop dragging!
Gotta keep going!
[in the distance]
The outcast!
On the old trail?
[in the distance]
Is she crazy?
Good, I'm gaining!
[in the distance]
Look! The outcast is catching up!
How'd she get up there?
Made it!
Come on now, hurry!
Keep at it!
I've trained my whole life for this.
They had a tribe, but I had the wilds.
Precision, not enough.
Must be perfect!
Come on, come on! You can make it!
Can't let them beat me now!
She didn't win! The outcast cheated!
An outcast win the Proving?
Never.
For she is a Brave now.
You did it!
As are you all, so long as
you put your trophy on the altar.
But it is Aloy,
once outcast, and now Brave,
who is first among…
AAH!
Uh!
Aah!
Aaaaa!
Aloy! Come!
Keep them pinned down until the others arrive.
Aaaah!
We can't stay here! That's the way out.
But we won't make it under fire.
They can't shoot if they're dead!
Keep them busy!
I'll find an angle.
Bast! BAST! Are you with us?
I'm with you!
Let's go!
Now!
[in the distance]
Too many of them!
We can't win!
[in the distance]
We can't hold them!
All-Mother help us!
[in the distance]
Kill the invaders!
Kill the defilers!
[in the distance]
They're too strong!
We can't stop them!
Quick! Run for the slip wire!
Kill them all.
No witnesses, no survivors.
[in the distance]
For All-Mother!
Oh no! There's more!
[in the distance]
They keep coming! How many are there?
Up on the ridge, there's more of them!
[in the distance]
Too many of them!
This is it for you.
[in the distance]
We can't hold them!
All-Mother help us!
Here!
[in the distance]
Kill the defilers!
Now, descend while we have a chance!
Aaah!
Vala! Vala!
No! Urk!
The red hair dies now!
Everyone forward!
Oof!
Turn your face to the sun, child.
NO!
Burn it all. Then to your task.
As you command.
Aloy!
Aloy.
Survive!